Testing can only show the presence of
bugs, but not their complete absence.
>> This is the creator of the OCaml
programming language, and I asked him
all about programming language design
and formal verification.
>> Oh my god.
>> [laughter]
>> Uh
yeah, I'm not a big fan of JavaScript.
And Rust is the finest language for
manual memory management. Manual memory
management is not always faster.
Maybe this will be the the decade of
formal verification of software.
>> If you took LLM-generated code and
turned it up, what languages would
become more popular? What languages
might fade away?
>> Woof.
Uh
>> Here's the full episode.
What sets OCaml apart from other
programming languages?
>> It it is a fine functional language.
Okay, you can
like functions by case over inductive
types and recursion and combine them
with combinators and then higher-order
functions and everything. So so it's
really a a a fine functional language,
but it's also a fairly decent systems
programming language.
And
um
so it has fully imperative power. It has
lots of
interesting control structures, um
exceptions, threads,
handlers for user-defined effects, which
we added recently.
Um and it has a very predictable cost
model execution model. So so when you
write your code, you have a pretty good
idea what what will take time and what
will be fast and what will be slow. And
that that's not the case for all
functional languages.
Some are pretty unpredictable. And and
then the implementation is also pretty
performant. Okay, so there's there's a
fairly decent compiler, not the best in
in its class, but the code is pretty
efficient. There's a very good allocator
and garbage collector with low latency,
so you don't have much pauses.
You don't have long long pauses and that
that's quite important when you do
things like network programming.
And and so
and so you can write systems
applications in
in in mostly functional style and and
with all the benefits of functional
programming.
And and so initially
OCaml wasn't
wasn't designed for those kind of
applications, okay? It was more for
things like theorem proving
or implementing domain-specific
languages.
And then we got some of the first users
who were from the systems community, in
particular
the Ensemble project in the late '90s at
Cornell University. So so it was a
network stack for a network protocol
stack for
reliable multicast and those kind of,
you know,
collaborative distributed applications
like collaborative editing or
multiplayer video games.
And and their first code was in C, of
course.
They were systems people, right? And and
it worked, but it was unmaintainable and
they couldn't extend it anymore. And
someone had the idea to try OCaml and
and so first the code became a lot nicer
and easier to to to evolve and the
performance was about as good
as the C code. And in particular, they
they had this uh
brilliant trick of running the garbage
collector while
packets are in flight, okay? Well,
once you've sent a packet, you're you're
idle for a few
microseconds and so you can run some
GC. It costs nothing.
And so they were very happy with that
and and and then there were some other
projects
like this using
OCaml for systems applications like the
Mirage Mirage uh
And and and yeah, and and and another
benefit or consequence of this uh
Ensemble project is that uh one of the
PhD students working on that was Yaron
Minsky, who then went to Jane Street and
and implemented their
their trading infrastructure in OCaml.
Uh so they are still today one of our
big users.
>> [snorts]
>> And and again, it's well, they do
automatic trading, so it must be fast
and reliable and
and no long pauses, but they also want
the elegance of functional programming.
And they want non- non-programmers to be
able to read and and their code like
financial engineers or quantitative
analysts.
And and so yeah, so OCaml is a fairly
good match for those kind of
applications.
>> I thought it might be interesting to
ground some of the conversation here by
making comparisons across programming
languages, maybe ones that people know
more.
When you think about Rust versus OCaml,
what are the big differences and the
pros and cons of the various design
decisions in those languages?
>> The the big dividing line is between
Rust and OCaml is
uh well, OCaml has automatic memory
management, garbage collection.
And Rust is uh is definitely uh a
language for manual memory management.
Uh it's a it's it's the finest language
for that I know for uh manual memory
management, okay? It means manages to to
make it
uh mostly safe
uh with with the discipline of uh
borrowing, etc. And uh and and tracking
ownership and so on. So it's in
infinitely uh uh safer than C or C++,
but it's still uh a language where you
uh allocate and free memory uh yourself.
And on the one hand, it gives more
control over what the program is doing.
On the other hand, it's still a big
responsibility. It's significantly
harder to write programs when you have
to to manage your memory, even with the
help of Rust
types.
So,
so yeah, so for me that that's kind of
the main
dividing line.
Otherwise, Rust has
Well, Rust has many of the high-level
features of functional languages, okay?
And in particular in in
data structures and ability to do
pattern matching and so on. So, it's a
very interesting design because they
really managed to
some kind of fusion between
you know, C or C++ style low-level
programming
and and some of the high-level
facilities of functional programming.
But still, that that divide, garbage
collection versus manual memory
management, remains.
>> So, it sounds like this is a performance
trade-off where you give more to the
programmer in exchange for higher
performance.
>> That's mostly true. That said,
manual memory management is not always
faster.
Or or or you need to be a very good
programmer so that it's always faster.
There's been some
some some mostly C++ code, for instance,
that that does a lot of copying
of objects just because you know, you're
you're not quite sure you're the only
owner. So, so you make a copy and now
you're the only owner. But the copying
is is quite costly in time and in and in
memory
bloat.
So, and and for those kind of
applications, a garbage collected
language is better.
And likewise with with
GC, you can work with shared sharing in
data structures, okay? And it's
perfectly safe.
Um
uh while um
uh
sharing is kind of limited with uh
Rust's uh
ownership discipline. Uh
there there are more constraints. And so
you may end up unsharing and so using
more memory.
>> It is surprising to me that um
that manual memory management would in
many cases be more performant than
automatic because for instance in in
other patterns in computer science, like
let's say letting the compiler optimize
things for you instead of optimizing
things yourself, I would have thought
that, you know, letting some system
manage memory for you rather than
manually mem- managing it would also be
better. So, why is there a difference
there?
>> Well, because garbage collection takes
place at run time. So, so we need from
time to time the
the program is no longer
computing, executing
what what you wrote. It is actually uh
uh scanning memory,
trying to find uh memory that is no
longer used. So, [snorts] so uh there's
there is uh a run time overhead.
And it can be uh depending on
applications 10%, 20%,
maybe sometimes 30%. Um but again uh
that that doesn't mean the whole program
is 30% uh
slower than if uh you had written it
with manual memory management because
there may have been uh other costs as
you said uh uh of of of manual memory
management. But yes, um there's
Uh um well, there's been a lot of
research on on trying to do um more, I'd
say, compile time automatic memory
management.
And you can do that to some extent, but
it it's for for for some some
programming styles where it's easy to
track the lifetime of of objects and and
and data blocks.
But in general, you still have quite a
bit of work to do at runtime.
>> I think a lot of people for garbage
collection, they might think of it as a
binary thing. It's either you have it or
you don't.
But I wonder in OCaml, is there some way
to
like turn down the memory management and
do some manual, so kind of like a
mixture to have the benefits of both?
>> So that's one of the things that the
Jane Street people are looking at. So
they have their
OCaml variant, Oxidized OCaml, which is
kind of OCaml with some inspiration from
Rust. So it's still very very
experimental, but yeah, they've been
playing with things like stack
allocation of some data structures
so that automatically deallocated when
the function returns, which is quite
cheap. Yeah, there there are a few
things you could try, but but I'm not
sure they are going to make such a big
difference. I remember doing this with a
student some experiments with stack
allocation of uh
of data structures a long time ago, and
you don't win as much as you would
think. See, garbage collection or
heap allocation is pretty cheap for
objects that have a very short lifetime.
Okay, if if they if they die before the
next garbage collector,
they they they will cost very little in
garbage collection time.
Uh but it's more expensive for
long-lived data structures, okay,
because those will be scanned and uh
analyzed uh
multiple times.
And stack allocation works for the first
kind of objects, things that
have short lifetime anyway.
So so you don't you don't win as much as
as as you think.
>> Um one of the most popular programming
languages JavaScript. Uh curious when
you think about the difference between
JavaScript and OCaml, what's the main
thing that comes to mind?
>> Yeah, I'm not a big fan of JavaScript.
Well, so JavaScript is uh Well, first
it's it's very dynamic. So,
type checking is entirely dynamic, but
it's more than that. I mean, pretty much
everything can be redefined at run time,
including, I don't know, the semantics
of method invocation, for instance. So,
so really some some pretty
fundamental aspects of the language
are very flexible. So, some people say,
"Oh, that's great. We can do lots of
meta meta programming, etc." And and to
me it it also it it's a big weakness. I
mean, it it is pro it makes programs
that are that can be very fragile
and [snorts]
also have some security issues. So, so
yeah, so JavaScript is the ultimate
dynamic language, in my opinion, while
OCaml is very static. Static typing,
static binding, pretty much everything
is fixed at compile time. Okay.
Uh
and then
Well, I guess it's a kind of a different
data data model. Uh JavaScript is a
little more object-oriented in in in the
way it it presents data. Maybe that's
not that important. And and to say one
good thing about JavaScript is that it
also contains a decent functional
language
inside. You know, there's there's a
little bit of a little core of
JavaScript which is basically Lisp
and and can be used to do a functional
programming if you want.
Um and and actually the the designer
of JavaScript, I think, was a former
Lisp person. I can't remember his name,
but
>> Brendan Eich, maybe?
>> Uh yeah, Brendan Eich, yeah.
There there was a little bit of heritage
from from Lisp to to JavaScript.
But a very dynamic kind of Lisp.
>> You said you weren't the biggest fan. Is
that just because of the dynamics or is
there some other aspect?
>> Yeah, mostly the dynamics. I think
They really went overboard with that.
This kind of meta meta object protocol
where you can really find the semantics
of
very basic operations like method
invocation. The fact that a method can
There's a lot of introspection. A method
can look at its own call stack, look at
its callers, look at the code of their
of its callers, which is a security
nightmare.
Um
All those things I think are completely
unnecessary and not conducive to good
programs.
Easily abused. Yeah. Easily abused.
>> I think on the topic of functional
languages compared to imperative
languages, there's this thought that uh
functional languages are kind of hard
harder to learn or maybe they have more
perceived complexity. And actually, I
when I my research, there's this popular
quote from the designer of Go, Rob Pike.
And he's talking about what they
intended to do with code with Go.
And he said, you know, the key point
here is the programmers are are
Googlers. They're not researchers. You
know, they they're young, fresh out of
school. They're not capable of
understanding a a brilliant language.
And I think, you know, that that thought
of a brilliant language is often
attributed to functional languages.
What do you think about is a language
like OCaml harder for programmers to
grasp than imperative languages?
>> I think functional programming is not
fundamentally harder, especially if you
have a little bit of mathematics
background. So, coming back to the quote
by
by Rob Pike, uh
I think it describes very much how they
go about hiring at Google. Okay, they
they they hire a lot of uh
engineers who are fresh out of of
college. Some of them have master's
degree, but And and then they train them
internally. Other other companies I I
try to to hire people with more
education and perhaps a more diverse
backgrounds.
Um and and yeah, so so Jane Street for
instance and and some of those use OCaml
as a filter on on who who they want to
hire.
Yeah, they have fewer applicants, but in
general they have more interesting
backgrounds. So
um
And perhaps one last thing I would like
to say, Python is 50% functional
language.
Okay. Uh
a lot of good Python code looks like
functional uh code with comprehensions.
So I think uh uh
people are already halfway uh through
through functional programming uh when
when when they are comfortable with
Python.
>> Yeah, when I was learning OCaml in
college, I think one thing that really
stood out to me and I thought was
interesting was this concept of type
inference
where the compiler is
kind of uh it knows the types of
everything implicitly in the the way
that the code is written.
Um can you explain uh type inference and
what the advantages are?
>> Well, the the basic idea is that uh you
don't have to declare the type of every
variable you introduce, every function
parameter, every local variable because
quite often the type can be deduced from
the uses of the variable. Okay? Uh like
if you do uh I don't know X equals
string length of S, uh then you kind of
know that S is a string and X is an
integer, right? Because that's what the
string length function uh that's the
type of string length and it it tells
you that.
Um so so that's the basic idea. Uh
now the the actual realization is a
little more complicated. Basically, you
need to collect a number of con- the
compiler needs to collect a number of
constraints and then try to solve them.
Uh see uh
well, if there's no solution, then it's
a type error. But, sometimes there are
several solutions and you must find good
criteria to choose one, otherwise you're
I mean, it also needs to be predictable
for for programmers.
Um, and often also you can you
um you can still put type annotation as
a programmer you can still put type
annotations if that makes the code
clearer.
So, I think the the the main advantage
is precisely to have less verbose code,
less verbose code. Well, you don't
you don't need to put types everywhere,
but only where they help uh
documentation and and documenting the
code and and making the making it easier
to read. Okay.
Uh, but quite often you
um for for like small local functions,
for uh short-lived temporary variables,
you you
the type is obvious from the context, so
let's just omit it.
>> If I'm trying to figure out how this
type inference works, the intuitive
example you said makes sense. But, uh
you mentioned it seems to be some sort
of system of equations that you solve or
something like that. Can you give a uh
concrete example maybe, you know, what
does that look like to the compiler?
>> Okay. Well, for a slightly more complex
example, say you have um
function with two parameters X and Y,
and then you do if X equals Y.
So, that tells you that X and Y have the
same type, but that still doesn't tell
you which type it is, uh assuming a
polymorphic uh equality comparison.
So, you've learned something about X and
Y, that they have the same type, but you
still don't know what the type is.
And later maybe you will learn something
about the type of X.
And now you will have determined the
type of Y as well.
So, so that's the kind of constraints
you you you accumulate and solve, um
little bit like, you know, Sudoku or uh
those kind of puzzles. And then there's
the interesting case where you don't
have enough constraints to find
a unique type.
So maybe in the end X and Y will be you
know they have the same type but it's
still unconstrained.
And and then that's where you
automatically get polymorphism for free.
Okay, the type checker said, "Okay,
those types are unconstrained so it can
work for any type."
So my function can take an X of any type
and a Y of the same type. Again, any
type and it's a polymorphic function.
So there's there's this beautiful I
think
phenomena phenomenon that that
polymorphism can be discovered
just by running type inference and
noticing that oh there are no
constraints so it must be polymorphic.
And and that was a great insight by
Robin Milner, the British computer
scientist pioneer who invented this ML
family of languages and and and this
kind of type inference in the 70s.
Polymorphism
was was
was not very well understood at the time
and so the fact that that he could have
he could introduce polymorphism so
easily in his language just as a
consequence of type inference
was a beautiful discovery.
>> So for type inference it seems like the
benefit is
you know the code is going to be a lot
more concise because we don't need to
write out all the types which seems
nice. But what are the tradeoffs of
adding type inference to a programming
language?
>> Well, as I said error messages can be
type error messages can be very
confusing
because
they not always point to the actual
source of the type error.
Okay.
The system may have done some some wrong
inferences and and and will report
though some of those inferences instead
of reporting the source the actual
source of the type error. So, it's been
it's been
the subject of much research.
And and there's there's no very
well-defined idea of the the source of a
type error, basically.
Um so, yeah. So, errors can be an issue.
Some features of type systems
are easy to combine with type inference,
to handle with type inference, and some
are harder.
Uh for instance, when it comes to
genericity, so I mentioned the
polymorphic parameter uh parametric
polymorphism, which which is very well
handled, but subtyping, the kind of
uh
thing you have in object-oriented
languages, is actually harder to to
combine with with type inference for
super technical reasons that I'm not
going to to go into.
Um so, so sometimes uh you have to make
a choice. Either you have type
inference, but it is less powerful,
uh or you you have uh full type
inference, but more restrictive type
system.
Uh
And and that that that that choice is
part of the language design, actually.
>> You mentioning this uh solver kind of
reminds me of the topic of formal
verification. Could you explain what
formal verification is?
>> Woo.
Well, it's the idea that um
um
you for for some programs, you want you
want strong guarantees that that that
the program is correct. Well, and and
guarantees that are hard to get just
with testing and and reviews, code
reviews.
Uh you know, there's uh this famous
quote by
uh Dijkstra, the the Dutch computer
pioneer,
uh which is which goes something like uh
testing can only show the presence of
bugs, but not their complete absence.
Uh because in general, there's an
infinite infinitely many inputs to your
program, and you cannot test them all.
So, you only test in your sample and
then sometimes you have surprises.
So, what if you want to make sure that
program is correct for an infinite
number of inputs?
And that's where you need to turn to
those so-called formal methods. So,
you're using mathematical reasoning,
you're using the uh
uh
static analysis algorithms on your on
your program to
really analyze all possible executions
of a piece of code and making sure that
it matches a specification.
The specification can be very simple
like the code will never crash
given well-formed inputs.
So, that that's a fairly simple
property, but still extremely useful
because code that crashes is always code
that can be attacked. It's always is
often security hole.
>> [sighs and gasps]
>> Um
so, for instance, all accesses within
array
all array accesses are within bounds.
That's a very simple property and it's
very hard to to ensure just by a type
system or just by testing. So, that's
[snorts] where you need some more
advanced formal verification.
And then there are
there are much more powerful specific
much more precise specifications that
you may want to check that can be where
the program always terminates. It can be
the program
doesn't [snorts] leak
confidential data. It can even be where
the program computes this mathematical
function
>> [snorts]
>> uh with
with an error floating point error under
I don't know, 10 to the minus six. Okay.
Something like that. Something very
precise like that.
And so, it's it's been really hot topic
in in
in in software sciences since the
uh since the '70s, I would say. There's
lots of techniques.
Some are just fully automatic like
static analysis, uh
but they're already pretty good at
finding bugs and making sure that some
bugs like array out of bounds are not
there.
And some
are a lot more interactive and and
require a lot more formal assistance to
write specifications and then do can so
called program proofs. So proving
mathematical statements about the
program.
>> I hear about it a lot more now which is
lean and these theorem provers.
Um what are those in this context and
how how are they used?
>> Uh so yeah so lean is is an example an
instance of the so called
provers or proof assistants.
Um so originally those were developed to
do mathematics on the computer. So not
nothing with
not formal verification of programs but
but they can also be used for formal
verification of programs. But the
initial motivation was really to do
mathematics with the help of the
computer.
Um where originally everyone focused on
automatic theorem proving. So having the
machine find proofs from
all by itself.
But that's very very difficult
and not necessarily what what
mathematicians need.
And so those proof assistants are more
like
where formal language is like like
programming languages but where you can
write mathematic definition mathematical
definitions mathematical statements
and they will help you prove. So so some
small proof steps they will do
automatically and for others the the
user still has to guide the prover
through through the major steps.
But the good thing is that the proof is
recorded also in a format that the
machine can understand and recheck.
So when you complete a proof in lean or
Coq, or Isabelle, or one of those tools,
and and it is rechecked, and and the
computer makes sure that all inferences
are justified, that you didn't forget
any case, that you uh you didn't use a
conclusion as an hypothesis, or where
all all kind of
problems you can have with a pencil and
paper proof.
And so, in the end, you get proofs that
are extremely uh
reliable, extremely credible.
Um and and it's been so so those tools
have been used a little bit uh
for well for for for some um
uh some big mathematical results, where
where the proofs are so big that that
that they can't be done just by humans.
They really need uh
computer assistance.
Uh
I think there's a recent example with a
weak uh Goldbach conjecture. Uh so, part
of the proof involved checking a whole
lot of inequality, maybe a thousand
inequalities involving several real
variables, and blah blah blah. And so,
um
computer assistance was really needed uh
to make sure that that everything was
checked, and and there was no no human
mistakes uh left.
And and maybe we'll talk about
generative AI later, but there's there's
also now a lot of interest in
conjunction with generative AI.
Uh AI is pretty good as that coming up
with plausible proofs.
Okay, but then they have to be checked
by humans.
Unless uh
AI writes a proof in one of those formal
languages like Lean, in which case it
can be checked by a machine, and that's
much more much more effective.
Um
So, yeah. So, it's it's the idea of of
using the machine to help you write
proofs and recheck proofs that you've
written yourself, or maybe with some
help from an AI.
And now those tools can also be used to
prove properties about programs.
And so so I I spent uh
many [clears throat] years uh uh
proving the correctness of a compiler, C
compiler,
uh using one of those tools, the the
Rock uh proof assistant.
Um so so basically um
when I'm proving about the compiler, so
it takes C code, it produces assembly
code, and
um proving that the assembly code is
faithful to the C code. So so there's no
miscompilation. The the compiler didn't
introduce a bug in the program that
wasn't there originally.
And and it's a fairly big proof because
compilers do complicated things about
programs, and then you have to define
exactly what it means to preserve the
semantics of a program. So you have to
define the semantics of your programming
languages. And and so so it's all a very
good use of those uh uh machines
uh of those proof assistants. Uh
the the same work could be done on
paper, but I mean this would be a proof
of several thousand pages, and nobody
would want to read it.
Nobody would trust it. It's just too
big. Uh and and it would be very hard to
evolve. Um
One good thing about
um those um
mechanized verifications of of programs
is that
uh
it can also help you evolve the program.
Okay? You can add new features and so
on, and and adapt your proofs, and be
really sure that you haven't introduced
a regression or things like that.
Um so yeah, so it's really uh
programming taken to a higher level. Um
And and today it's quite expensive. Um
it takes a lot more time to to prove a
program than to write it in the first
place. But maybe this is getting a
little better.
Um
Yeah, and I should also mention another
great uh of certified software is the
it's a microkernel, the SEL4
microkernel,
uh developed in Australia, and which is
used as an hypervisor in in some in some
applications.
And so it is uh
is
really like 8,000 lines of extremely
technical C code that that, you know,
manipulates uh
uh processes and uh
capabilities and security tokens and so
on. And it's been proved correct. Every
line has been proved correct. And that
that's a very big achievement.
>> When you mentioned the example of
verifying a mathematical proof, that
uh makes sense to me. When you talk
about proving something about a program,
it's a little bit more abstract to me or
I'm having some trouble visualizing.
Could you give a concrete example like
uh maybe some trivial program that we're
trying to prove something about it and
how that uh theorem prover would work.
>> Let's say
you have a function that takes three
numbers, X, Y, Z, and um returns the
average of those numbers.
Okay?
Um
only
yeah, and and maybe
you're using a not completely obvious
formula like uh
T equals X plus Y and then T equals T
plus Z and then um T equals T divided by
3 and then return T. Okay? So not that
exactly is the formula for the
average.
Uh and you want to prove that that
function is correct. So so you want to
prove that
it it returns uh
X plus Y plus Z divided by 3. And maybe
you will have to make it clear whether
you're rounding up or rounding down.
If you're using integers or
floating-point numbers, you know, it's
not a exact arithmetic, so
>> [snorts]
>> um
So, yeah, you you'll have to to say
exactly what you mean by divided by
three.
>> [snorts]
>> And then, uh if you are in a language
like C, you can have arithmetic
overflows.
Okay? When you compute X + Y or
+ Z,
um
you can overflow the range of
representable representable integers,
and in C, it's it's a bug. It's an
undefined behavior.
So, typically, you will want to put a
so-called precondition on your function
saying, "Okay,
uh if you call me, call me with numbers
that are between, I don't know, zero and
1 million for instance, but no bigger
than that." And and then, the prover
will check that no overflow can occur in
this case.
Um okay? And so So, basically, you have
the precondition that says, "Okay, these
are safety guarantees um
that must hold of the parameters,
otherwise, anything can happen."
And then, there will be a little bit of
kind of symbolic execution of the
function body
that says, "Okay, when you T equals X +
Y, then T plus equals Z, then T
equals three, then in the end, T is X +
Y + Z divided by three, provided no
overflow occurred."
And then, you put that with a
precondition that says,
"There cannot be any
overflow," and you get your final
result.
Okay? So, basically, you're stating a
contract for your function, the pre-
hypotheses on the arguments,
uh guarantees on the results.
And
uh and and you want to prove or analyze
the function body to show that this
contract is respected.
I hope it's a little more concrete.
>> So, it it sounds like a lean will help
you basically take in some invariants
about a program and kind of propagate
them through line by line and uphold
them. And so you can say something about
>> Yes.
Maybe not Lean by itself. Well, a
program prover a program prover will do
exactly what you say.
And for Lean to be able to do it, you
still need to teach it a little bit
about the semantics of your programming
language.
Okay, that
what does a plus means, what does
assignment means, okay? Lean Lean is
mathematics. You don't assign in
mathematics. You don't say x equals x
plus one or or or
or you're just comparing x and x plus y
and it's always false. There's no
assignment in mathematics. There's
assignment in many programs. So you need
to
make it explicit that
there are [snorts] actually three
different states for the t variable,
three different values and and
and relate [clears throat] those values
to
Well, the program defines what those
values are and then a prover like Lean
can can reason about those three
successive values.
Because now you're in you're in
mathematics.
And and that that kind of bridge between
programs and their mathematical meaning
is called semantics. That that the field
of semantics of programming languages
has been a big topic in in PL research
since the the '60s at least.
>> Am I understanding then that
like a pure functional programming
language, the gap between mathematics
and
the actual symbols is much smaller than
an imperative?
>> Absolutely. Yeah, you're you're
absolutely right.
And that's one of the reasons why
people who do formal methods don't like
assignment, don't like imperative
features.
Purely functional style is much closer
to mathematical style, so much easier to
reason going
There can still be few discrepancies
between the program and the math. Uh,
for instance, functional programs may
not terminate.
They may loop forever. Um, mathematics
doesn't like that. So, so you need a way
to to reason about termination.
Um, and uh
and also yeah, sometimes for instance,
the the arithmetic you get in the
programming language is not
uh, integer arithmetic or is not
uh, real reals. [clears throat] You
know, it's floating point, it's not
reals. So, so you still have to
uh, account for that
gap. Uh, but you're you're absolutely
right that the gap is much shorter for
functional programming. And and uh
in the experience of CompCert, my my
verified compiler,
I think the the first decision was to
write it in a purely functional style
so that it would be easier to to reason
about it later.
>> You mentioned the the specifications
that we could prove, and one of them was
proving that the program terminates, but
I thought that's a famously
difficult or impossible. I forgot
exactly that the halting problem, right?
So, how how is that something that you
could prove?
>> Okay, so what the
um computability theory says is that
there is no algorithm that will always
that can always say
this program terminates or this program
doesn't terminate.
Um,
so so there will always be some very
weird programs for which your your
analyzer your your automatic termination
analyzer will produce a wrong result
or will not terminate itself.
Uh, so it will not work.
Um, uh but
still for for many programs, you can
succeed. Okay, you can write automatic
termination analyzers that will work for
a large uh class of programs.
And then the termination analysis,
termination proof can also be done by
hand by by a mathematician. Okay, so
So, perhaps
a human can can see through those weird
Turing programs that that are hard to
prove to terminate and
and and recognize the trick.
But, anyway, so yeah, it's a hard
problem and all all program verification
tasks are are difficult pro
problems, okay? Uh
They are pretty much all undecidable.
So, you know that there there is no
static analyzer that will always
find all problem all problems in all
programs.
>> [snorts]
>> But, still you can try, okay? You can
try for specific problems, for specific
programs and and get some very useful
results out of them out of that.
You only need to be able to do it for
the cases that are of interest to you,
the programs you really care about.
>> OpenAI, Anthropic, Cursor, and Vercel
all use this product to make their lives
better.
And the problem it solves is when you're
building SaaS or an AI product and you
want to sell to other companies, there's
all these requirements you need to meet.
There's SSO, there's SCIM, there's RBAC,
there's audit logs. These are all things
that take time to integrate, but aren't
the main focus of your app. WorkOS is an
API layer that lets you meet all of
these requirements in just a few lines
of code. So, let's say you have a new
SaaS product and you want to sell to
other companies, WorkOS will solve all
of these critical feature gaps for you.
You can check them out at workos.com to
learn more and get started. And I
appreciate them for supporting my work
and sponsoring this podcast. One thing
[snorts] I saw when I was researching
OCaml is that
uh in 2022, OCaml added multicore
support. And but from my memory, I
remember multi-core processors became
standard much earlier than that. And so,
I figured there might be some unique
engineering challenge in adding that
support. So, yeah, what what happened
there and what made it difficult?
>> Uh well, there were
engineering challenges, that's for sure.
There there were also some language
design issues.
So, so but let's talk about the
engineering challenges first.
Um so, it's true that that when you have
a a language with with a runtime system
memory allocator or garbage collector
uh
well, at least the one of for for OCaml
was really designed with sequential
executions in mind.
So, if you have if you add a shared
memory concurrency, then you need a
garbage collector or a memory allocator
that that that that can work
concurrently. And that's actually quite
difficult.
Uh at least if you want them to be fast.
Of course, you
you could always, you know, take take
take a lock at at every operation in the
heap, but then uh you would
sequentialize your programs. Basically,
they they they would run as slowly as a
single processor. So, so that's not
interesting. So, yeah, so there were
engineering challenges. Um um yeah, I
was at least initially quite quite
reluctant to
uh basically re-implement a complete uh
garbage collector and and uh memory
allocator or large parts of the runtime
system. That's what we did eventually
with uh as well, it was done mostly by
the team at OCaml Labs at Cambridge
University.
>> [snorts]
>> Uh but yes, it was a really big rewrite.
Um but then I said there's also a
language design issue.
Which is that for for the longest time
well
uh
is
now when when you say uh
multi-core
processors and so on, pretty much
everyone
and language support for multi-core
processors, everyone thinks about
language support for shared memory
concurrency.
You know, this model where you have
several sites of control and they access
the same memory
and basically the sites communicate by
modifying the memory and someone else is
going to notice.
You know, it and
I've never liked this model of of
communication.
I mean, it's a bit like if you want to
communicate with your neighbor then then
you you you break into their houses and
their house and then you move the
furniture around and then when they are
back they say, "Oh, something something
was moved so it's probably Iron who's
trying to tell us something."
Maybe you could just meet your
neighbors, you know? And and that would
be things like message passing
which is a completely different form of
communication, much higher level.
So, yeah, so for the longest time I was
really interested in message passing
concurrency.
And there's for instance a functional
language called Erlang that was built on
around those ideas and that I found
quite interesting.
However, I never got to to have a
decent language design and
everyone was saying, "No, but but it
it's it's too costly. It's not
effective. There's too much copying of
data.
With shared memory you can you can share
some kind of huge database in memory. If
you don't modify it too much, then
basically the sharing is the the
concurrency is free.
While with message passing we'll have to
exchange a lot of data so
to to get the same effect so so you will
pay more for it.
Anyway,
so
so okay, so
starting with Java I guess and then C
C++ 2011 there was this idea that okay,
we we we need to expose shared memory
concurrency to the programmers.
But then comes the problem of the memory
model, which is that
what happens when there's a race, for
instance, when when two
uh two threads want to access the same
uh location, and maybe they want to
modify it in different ways.
And so, sometimes parts of the C C++
standard says, "It's undefined behavior.
Anything can happen." But still, you
need to give a little more guarantees.
Uh at the other end of the spectrum,
there's a so-called uh sequential
consistency, which says, "Well, what
happens is like an interleaving of reads
and writes of your program."
You don't know which interleaving, but
there is an interleaving.
But that doesn't work with modern
uh processors, multi-core processors.
They reorder memory accesses in in very
clever ways to get more performance. And
so, viewed from the program, it's very
hard to predict what they are actually
doing.
And so, you need to give your
programmers, when you're designing a
language with shared memory concurrency,
you need to give your programmers some
guarantees about uh the ordering of
reads and writes, concurrent reads and
writes, while not constraining the
hardware too much.
And it's very difficult. So, Java went
through like five different iterations
of the memory model. Some were too
strict, some were too lax, some were
kind of in
inconsistent. They were were were making
predictions, impossible predictions,
where where the past depends on the
future.
>> [snorts]
>> Crazy, really crazy stuff.
Uh then C C++ 11 did a little better,
but still extremely complex memory
model. And so, when we wanted to add
when the especially the OCaml Labs
people wanted to add uh shared memory
concurrency to OCaml, we had to also
agree on a memory model
that would be
exposed to the programmers.
And and that's also took quite a bit of
a design uh quite a bit of time to come
up with a good design. Uh
And I
I think it's it's
better and easier to understand and use
than the one of Java, but the the OCaml
memory model is still quite complicated.
And
And sometimes I feel sorry our users are
are exposed to that. Okay. Uh
Uh
So, that that that explains why it took
so long.
Solving the
engineering challenges, but also
having a
agreeing on the memory model and what
kind of guarantees we're going to give
to programmers.
Oh, yeah. I forgot to say one thing,
which is that
So, C and C++ there's a lot of things
you can say, "Oh, it's just undefined
behavior or anything can happen."
In type-safe languages like Java and
OCaml, you want to give stronger
guarantees. Okay. Maybe many things can
happen, but your data should should
remain well-typed.
Okay. Typically, you don't want to
expose an object to another thread
before it's been fully initialized, for
instance.
Um And And that's that's actually very
hard to guarantee in your memory model.
And then
you have to implement that memory model,
so your compiler also needs to take
extra
precautions to to to guarantee this. So,
yeah, type safety in the presence of
shared memory concurrency is is not
obvious at all.
And so, that's why it took so long.
>> So, in Python, I know there's the famous
GIL or the global interpreter lock. What
is that lock protecting? Is it the the
cleanup of objects on the heap or is it
something else?
>> Among other things, yes. So, yeah, we we
had the same thing in OCaml before
before
multicore OCaml with
>> [snorts]
>> with Marstin. So, yeah, well, basically,
the idea that when when your runtime
system is not thread-safe, as we said,
you can protect the non-thread safe
functions by your lock so that
they will never be executed
concurrently.
But if you take the lock at every
allocation and release it,
you take and release the lock for every
allocation and it's just too slow
anyway.
And so the idea is that
you take the lock when you enter Python
code, let's say, and you start executing
Python code.
But you can still release it when you do
input output for instance, when you're
going to block for a long time.
Or when you're calling into C code that
that
that is thread safe and is not going to
use your runtime system.
Then you can release the lock and some
other
Python thread can take it and execute.
So you get a little bit of concurrency.
You can overlap computations in your
high-level language with IO or
computation is a low-level language in
another language.
But you still have mutual exclusion
between your
between two threads running Python or
running OCaml before before multicore
OCaml.
So so you get some benefits like
concurrent IO, but you don't get any
parallelism.
Okay, yeah. You don't get a speed up for
computations.
And so so yeah, so we used to have this
this this GIL in in in OCaml as well.
And
so you can get rid of it, but in
general, you need to redesign at least
the garbage collector and and memory
allocator.
There's probably a few places in the
OCaml runtime system that still use
locks to
to to ensure mutual exclusion like in
the IO subsystem.
And and some phases of the garbage
collector, I think that there's a phase
which is kind of stop the world where
you need to make sure that everyone
no no no camel code is is running.
So for a short time you need to make
sure that everyone is stopped and then
do a little bit of work to finish the GC
and then you can restart everyone.
Um so yeah, that these are tricky things
and I don't know what the Python people
are up to with their GIL if if they
finally managed to remove it or
they're still working on it but I I I've
heard they're making progress. So.
>> Yeah, you mentioned Python calling into
C and I've seen that pattern before of a
higher level language interfacing with a
lower level one. How does that binding
typically work?
>> Oh, it's another can of worms.
Um
Well, there are two aspects. There are
there are the the control flow and there
are the
the data.
So the control part is is
not that hard. So yes, you need you need
a mechanism so that your your Python
interpreter or your OCaml compiled code
will actually jump to the C function.
Uh so for OCaml basically you you tell
your OCaml compiler that this function
is not implemented in OCaml, it's
actually implemented by a C function and
you give its name and then the compiler
will emit a call to the C function using
the C calling conventions which are not
exactly the same as the OCaml calling
convention but
the compiler knows about that. And so it
will
call the C function maybe through a
little bit of glue code or whatever and
then the C function will execute and and
return back to the OCaml code.
Um
That's relatively easy. Uh now the hard
part is uh data
uh like function arguments and function
results
because OCaml and C have different data
representations.
Uh for instance, a floating point number
in in OCaml is generally boxed, so it's
allocated in the heap and handled
through a pointer. So, it's more like a
double star in in C
and it's not a double, which is not
allocated.
Just it's in a register.
Um so
so typically the C code needs to use a
so-called foreign function interface, so
some C function and macros provided by
OCaml to access the OCaml data, the
OCaml arguments, you know, extract the
part that it needs, the the numbers, the
uh
uh yeah, another example is arrays. Um
in OCaml when you have
a two-dimensional array, it's actually
an array of arrays. So, viewed from C,
it's an array of pointers to arrays.
While in C, an array of arrays is
there's no intermediate pointer, so it's
not the same representation. And so, you
have to explain to C or give C some
functions and macros to to access uh
elements in OCaml arrays. Uh it's not
exactly the same code that that that
that that you would do to access a C
array from C.
Okay, so you need accessors, but now if
you want to uh
if your C code wants to return some
complex results like a list, an array,
and so on, it needs to allocate it in
the OCaml heap. So, it needs to ask the
runtime system to do some heap
allocation and then fill the uh
>> [snorts]
>> heap blocks correctly. And then this
allocation can can trigger a garbage
collection, so the C code that also kind
of cooperate with a garbage collection
with registration mechanisms, etc., etc.
So, so there's quite a bit of work to to
be done.
And and uh and then different foreign
function interfaces
arrange this work differently. So,
there's a base FFI for OCaml, basically
uh it's a C code that must do all the
work.
But but then it can be very fast and
quite optimized.
Uh but there are other FFIs like the C
types FFI in OCaml where most of these
data conversion and and mediating
between two data formats is automated.
Uh you start basically with a
description of the the the the the C
type of the C function and and you can
automate some of those conversions. But
sometimes it can be tricky it can be
expensive. For instance, [snorts] you
may end up copying the whole array while
your C code only needs to access two or
three elements in it.
Um okay. So there's lots of trade-offs.
And quite frankly it it's a dirty part
of of programming language
implementation. Uh the the OCaml FFI is
not that clean, but if you look at the
Java FFI for instance, it's also quite
complicated. And for Python I've I've
never tried. Uh so I I don't know what
it looks like.
Uh
but yeah, it's a it's a necessity.
Uh but but it can be quite hard because
the data models are different between
the two languages.
>> So to kind of get the big picture, on
the OCaml side, there's an interpreter
which is a program running in
application space that is interpreting
your OCaml code. And then at some point
in the OCaml code, it says
do some, you know, load this C program.
And the C program is a binary somewhere.
And the OCaml interpreter then starts to
load those instructions and execute
them.
>> Okay. So actually this is the third
aspect that I didn't touch.
So so OCaml well, there's an interpreter
mode, but in general we compile. We
compile to assembly code and then
machine code.
And so
so in in in compiled mode,
what what you say is
how you put together the OCaml code and
the C code is done by the the linker,
the C linker. So so
So basically someone else is doing that
for us. And and and it's not that
different from linking together two
object files produced by C or two object
files produced by OCaml.
But you write that for for more
interpreted
languages, there's also the question of
how you load the C code.
Generally you know you use the dynamic
loading like interface dlopen for
instance in in in Unix.
So and and and then there's a little bit
of introspection. So so at at run time
the interpreter will query the C
libraries and where is the address of a
function named foo? And then it will
find the address and use that to
manufacture a call. So yeah, if you're
in an interpreted setting or
or bytecode compiled setting like
Python, it's there's this additional
level of complexity on top of it.
>> I see. I see. Okay, so if I had a mixed
OCaml C program
to my computer it's just one binary or
one one blob.
>> In in in the simplest case, yes.
There are also dynamic loading
facilities in OCaml, but I don't want to
get into that because I'm a firm
believer in static linking. I think
programs should be statically linked so
that there's no surprise when you run
them. Okay, like oh, where is this DLL
or DLL not found for instance problems.
But
of course you lose a little bit in
flexibility.
But yeah, I think the static static
linking has a lot to
is is actually quite useful in in that
it it guarantees a lot of things. It
checks a lot of things at link time that
you
don't have to check again at run time.
>> We mentioned earlier in the conversation
talking a little bit about LLM generated
code. I thought that might be
interesting to cover. Um and in one
interview you talked about the danger of
almost correct code. So, plausible code
but it's it's wrong that an LLM can
produce. And what are your thoughts on
you know how to address that kind of
problem?
>> It's it's it's a tough problem. I mean
you
um
globally I'm a little bit skeptical
about generative AI. Oh, of course they
they they
they can do amazing things that were
unthinkable like a few years ago.
But there's also
there's always some errors. Okay. It's
it's
you can't really trust
oh
what's what's being produced by by
generative AI.
And so
the the
uh
in principle humans should be there to
check the output and
and fix errors or ask the LLM to fix its
own errors
until the result is actually usable. But
of course it's very hard because well
there's a slot problem. Okay.
AI's produce so much it's so it's so
easy to produce
uh
to produce large number large quantities
of text of code or pictures or whatever
that that that in the end
there's there's there's no human
no no no human time to to check it all.
So,
recently I heard a
uh well someone working in an AI startup
who was enthusiastic about
uh
AI generated code thing that thanks to
Genady AI is a cost of programming is
dropping to zero.
But well, the cost of writing code
maybe, but
what about you know checking it,
making sure it is correct, um
that it does what we want, that
well, that cost is not zero at all.
>> Uh-huh.
>> And and for me
every new line of code is a liability.
So you you have to test it, you have to
check it, maybe you have to do formal
verification. You have to
evolve it, maintain it later. So so no,
I don't want huge amounts of code, okay?
I want I want
50 lines of code that have been
thought that have been polished over the
years.
So anyway, I'm not getting that with AI.
And and and I think that's the problem.
And this idea that humans will be there
to check the output of Genady AI is just
wrong.
No, they they they are not available for
that. They
There's too much of it and it's
and it's [snorts] not it's not pleasant
either, okay? I mean, I don't think it's
a good way to to to split the work
between machines and and humans.
So anyway, so maybe there will be some
social
solution like big
>> [snorts]
>> no to AI slop movements. So we we we're
trying to see that in some open source
projects that that refuse AI generated
contributions because there's just too
many.
>> [snorts]
>> I know that well for for for OCaml and
especially for Coq Certified have have
received some uh
uh issues, a lot of issues that were
obviously generated by AI. And there was
maybe one good issue among 10 reports,
okay? And and and each report was
several page long and it's, you know,
very detailed explanations, and repro
case that in the end doesn't repro
anything or repro reproduces something
else. And but but it takes time to to go
through all those things, and and maybe
at some point I will say no to to AI
generated contributions.
Okay. But maybe there's also a bit of a
technical solution,
which is, as as we said earlier,
to have AI produce proofs,
so evidence that
its creation is correct. So, as I said,
this is starting to work for
mathematical proofs. Some generally the
AIs are able to produce proofs both in
English and in the formal language of
the Lean prover, for instance. And so,
you can get
a Lean to recheck the proof and get some
confidence. You still need to be very
careful about the statement,
because sometimes
AIs will change the statement or the
definitions to make the proof easier.
That happens.
And
also, you you should be careful about
so-called self-formalizations, where the
the AI also comes up with some
definitions and some statements
by parsing a PDF file or whatever, and
and sometimes it introduces errors at
that point.
So, anyway, there's still need need for
human review, but
on smaller quantities of of text and and
mathematical text.
And maybe one day it will also work for
program proof. So, when an AI generates
a program, it might it be able to
generate some Lean proof or whatever,
that that the program satisfies some
specification.
Um
So, I I think it is possible.
Um but now the question will be where
does the specification come from?
It's always been a big issue for formal
methods.
It's not just that verification is hard,
but agreeing on the spec can be
can be difficult, too.
And well, mathematicians
have a lot of experience, you know, in
in stating
finding a definition that they find
interesting and stating theorems that
that that
that they believe
should be true or or or that that will
um
mean something.
Computer programmers are less good with
that. And it's fairly easy to come up
with specifications that are
inconsistent for instance or impossible.
Uh so, remember this this average
function
where there was a a precondition of the
three numbers three arguments saying
they must not be too big.
But say
maybe you you can end up with a
precondition that that just cannot be
satisfied.
And and
and and at this point, the body of the
function will always be verified, okay?
Even if it's completely wrong because
because the assumption says
basically this function cannot be
called.
Um and and so, you get a false sense of
confidence.
Okay, you verified something, but but
it's actually unusable.
And and and that that's a fairly
delicate point
where I'm not sure LLMs are going to or
AI is going to help much.
Uh
but but it's a problem with formal
methods in general. And and some
possibilities include
uh
the ability to test specifications for
instance.
Um
so, instead of using your test suite to
to to see if your code works out, you
can also use it to see if your spec um
um
it checks out. Um
those kind of things, but um
yeah, we we're kind of moving some of
the difficulties from the programming
phase to the uh specification phase, but
we still have some problems.
Anyway, so that might be a way to to
deal with the um
uh AI-generated code and and and develop
some confidence in it.
>> You know, LLM-generated code is becoming
extremely popular, and I think there's a
lot of potential downstream consequences
on this on the programming language uh
landscape.
And I thought it might be interesting to
hear your thoughts on speculating. Like,
imagine 10 years from now, if you took
LLM-generated code and turned it up,
how might you think that the programming
language
landscape might change?
>> Yeah, a couple of years ago uh someone
asked me about that, and and there was
there was a a concern that the training
data would be um there wouldn't be
enough training data in OCaml
uh for for an LLM to really learn how to
program in OCaml.
And it's true that there's less OCaml
code in the wild than uh JavaScript
code, for instance.
Uh but apparently
um uh contemporary LLMs do do do well
with with uh the amount of uh of OCaml
code uh
they have.
Uh
maybe because there's enough, maybe
because learning has become a little
more efficient, maybe because uh well,
there's there's there's less OCaml code
than JavaScript code, but maybe the
OCaml code is better quality average
on an average. I don't know. Anyway, uh
maybe LLMs are getting better also to to
transfer knowledge from that they've
learned from one language to another.
That that could be. Um I have no idea
how those things work.
But yeah, so so the latest feedback I've
got about LLMs and
well, yeah,
generative AI and OCaml is that the the
OCaml code generated is is quite decent
and quite similar in quality to
to more popular languages.
And one thing that seems to help the
generative AI is a type system. So the
fact that there's some static checking
just of the types uh
uh it's already uh effective in, you
know, the
uh avoiding some some errors and maybe
uh encouraging the LLM to like like
declare types
uh first. Um so so give give some type
structure to the program.
All right.
Um
And now from 10 years from now,
it's it's it's difficult to guess. So,
will it be the more the more popular
languages of today that will be even
more popular because of generative AI?
Will it be the safer languages of today
that will be more popular with AI
because uh
well, because there's fewer errors in
the end?
Um I'm hoping it will be the the safer
languages, but uh
I really don't know.
>> I've seen in the industry, there's a few
cases where because it's so easy to
generate code, uh massive rewrites are
something that would have been very
infeasible in the past are very
realizable now. So, if there's an
existing project where they chose a
programming language for whatever reason
in the past, they could translate the
entire thing into another language
with reasonable confidence. Given that
kind of environment, which programming
languages would you expect more people
would switch to because they they want
to switch to it but they weren't able to
in the past but now it's cheaper so they
can.
>> Well, so today
it seems I've heard mostly about C and
C++ to Rust
translations
hoping that the generated Rust code will
be safer.
He said I've seen at least one project
when the generated Rust code is entirely
in unsafe blocks. So so it's really kind
of line by line translation of the C
code, you know, it's
but well,
but maybe it can still be used as a
starting point for making it safer
later.
So
yeah, I would say today
I can imagine
significant efforts being being done
with Rust as the as a target language.
In the functional world, I'm not quite
sure. Well, maybe or well
>> [snorts]
>> maybe functional language to one of
those proof assistants
like like Lean or Coq because they they
also have
programming languages functional
programming languages in them much more
restricted but much more amenable to
proofs. So
maybe for a few projects that that could
be interesting as again as a first step
towards a formal proof as we as we said
earlier.
>> When you compare industry versus
academia,
today where would you say most of the
innovation in programming languages
comes from? And also has that changed
over time?
>> Okay, well, I think the
most of the innovations
have come from industry lately.
And that wasn't the case in the early
days of computer science.
If you think of I mean, the the totally
innovative languages like like Algol,
Lisp,
uh
um
Prolog, uh Smalltalk were were developed
in mostly academic settings. Well,
Smalltalk was Xerox PARC, which was an
industrial research lab, but very very
far away from
uh industrial customers.
Uh and then there were, you know, much
more
uh practical languages and ugly uh
uglier languages developed typically at
IBM like Fortran, COBOL, PL/I, etc.
Um and then um
so so really the idea that the the the
nice ideas come from academia and and
mature there. Uh
And then uh well, the nice ideas from
academia started to to be transferred by
industry much much more quickly. I'm
thinking of well, C and especially C++
and then Java, which really uh took uh
ideas like object-orientation and uh
well, garbage collection, automatic
memory management uh in in
um in industry.
All right. Before Java, it was just, you
know, uh crazy academics in the ivory
tower that were using garbage collected
languages, right? It was completely
impossible to have that in enterprise
compu- computing. And Java came and 2
years later everyone was doing garbage
collection and
being very happy about it.
>> [snorts]
>> Uh and then there were well, Java also
popularized type safety um
bytecode verification. Well, some some
pretty advanced techniques of the '90s.
And if you look at further developments,
uh
I don't know, Swift for instance
popularized the idea of algebraic data
types and pattern matching. Uh and then
Rust uh and
uh Uh, well, Rust is even more
spectacular, I would say, because uh,
well, algebraic data types, garbage
collections, etc., those were already
present in in academic languages like,
well, Camel, for instance. But, uh,
Rust really took very recent research
results of the 2000s and safe low-level
programming that were basically never
implemented in any language, and managed
to do a a consistent whole,
uh, from that.
And so, I'm I'm really admiring it.
And I have the impression that
well, uh,
uh, I would have loved if if Rust came
out of academia, uh, but I'm not sure it
would have been possible, because it's
also a huge effort, and you really need
uh,
the backing of of a big, uh, company.
But, still, I'm not I'm not sad because,
uh,
I think it's also a very good sign that
industry is interested in new
programming languages.
You know, at at some point,
in in the '90s, well, pretty much when I
was hired uh, at INRIA on a research
position, uh,
uh, when I was hired as someone who had
developed uh,
first versions of OCaml, well,
predecessor of OCaml, and who was
working on type systems for programming
languages, and so on.
Uh, but then some people told me, but
there's no future in programming
language research, right? Industry has
decided it will be C++ forever.
So, deal with it. Uh, maybe maybe you
could do software engineering, and not
not not PL research.
Uh,
and then Java came a few years later,
and and showing that no, uh,
industry hasn't [clears throat] decided
on a functional on a on a particular
programming language. Industry is still
in interested in new programming
languages. Industry still thinks that a
new programming language can be part of
the solution to to software problems.
And and I find it extremely encouraging.
We are not stuck with with bad languages
from the past. Well, there's a lot of
legacy code, of course, but but they're
still
uh um
real interest for for for better
languages, and I think this will
continue, and I think it's good for for
the computing field.
>> In 2018, there was a interview that you
did, and they asked you what are the
most interesting and important problems
to focus on in the coming years.
And you called out the difficulty of
programming, you know, GPUs, cuz they
were using dialects of C, shoddy tools,
and also the challenges in verifying
machine learned code, basically. Um and
that sounds pretty relevant today, but
what would you say your answer is today?
>> So, yeah, I think well, for for the um
um the question of how we program
massively parallel hardware,
I think we we've made a little bit of
progress recently with things like the
uh MLIR initiative um
on the on LLVM, or some domain-specific
languages uh like Halide, which are
pretty good. You know, those tensor uh
domain-specific languages for tensor
computations are getting a little
better.
Um but still, I find it a little bit
frustrating that I cannot do uh I don't
know, theorem proving on a GPU. Uh I
have absolutely no idea how to go about
that.
Uh and in part by by by lack of uh an
appropriate language, okay? Uh
uh
So, I'm I'm not ready to program the GPU
pipelines
at the very low level myself, so
So, and and I think it's more general. I
think we're we're not using uh all these
GPU and other highly parallel hardware
as much as we could. Yeah, so verifying
applications that have been learned or
generated
or generated by AI also and it's still a
pretty
hot issue.
Back in 2018 I was more thinking of of
verifying simple neural networks like
those used for I don't know computer
vision
or self-driving cars or or or some
numerical computations like you know
weather prediction and so on. So so
specialized LLMs but you still want some
guarantees about
what they produce that they cannot
produce completely inconsistent outputs
for instance. There were some some
attempts in in in the last years at
using static analysis tools and
basically program verification tools
applied to LLMs
but well it it it doesn't scale.
LLMs are big.
Sorry.
Neural networks are big.
And for LLMs there's also
a distinct lack of specification. Okay.
You don't really know what's a good
answer from an LLM.
Well you know it when you see it but you
cannot write a mathematical
specification of it. So so that part is
probably over. What I would say are the
big problems for today yeah probably
maintaining software quality despite
AI's love despite a lot of pressure to
throw away traditional software
development techniques using
LLMs as an AI as much as we can to do
mechanized proofs so proofs that can be
checked by machines.
Maybe this will be the the decade of
formal verification of software. We've
been waiting for that for 50 years so
maybe it will it will finally take off.
>> What's your top book recommendation for
software engineers and why?
>> Well this this is an old one, the
Programming Pearls by Jon
I think I read it when I was a PhD
student, but I think it's it's nice as
showing how very talented programmers
work, [snorts] how they think about
their programs. So, it's it's it's it's
a combination of choosing the right
algorithms,
expressing them clearly,
uh knowing when to stop,
when when to use a simple algorithm,
where where
when a more complicated one is not
needed,
uh having a sense of elegance in in the
code you write, um
uh having a feeling for where the
problem is when when the the code
misbehave. So, all all that kind of
things that are hard to communicate, and
I think those those pearls
that are very easy to read, uh
and and and don't use any complicated
data structures, don't use any
complicated language. I mean, it it's
it's kind of timeless, you know.
Um
I think those pearls are are good
illustration of that.
Uh so, if you haven't read it, it's it's
a classic, but
I think it's a nice reading.
Nice read. Uh the second one is a little
more controversial, I guess.
So, in the How to Design Program, which
is a fairly ambitious title as well.
And this comes from the Scheme
community, okay, Abelson and Findler,
Flatt, and Krishnamurthi.
Um and and those people have developed
uh well, the Scheme community is famous
for having developed uh pedagogical
resources that are
I mean, ways to teach programming uh
that that go beyond teaching functional
programming, basically.
And so, so there was the
the MIT [clears throat]
Course Structure and Interpretation of
Computer Programs, which was quite
famous, and this is kind of a more
modern
twist on on on similar ideas.
And and and
I find this book interesting because
well, it it it really teaches you the
way of functional programming
a way to functional programming. It can
be very irritating sometimes, very
opinionated, very
um almost mystical sometimes, but
but it's also
another
great attempt at at trying to
communicate
how experienced programmers go about uh
designing a program
uh
even before writing the first line.
Okay. And and then how
given a language like Scheme, which is
pretty flexible, how the code kind of
follows uh naturally.
>> You know, knowing what you know now, if
you could go back to when you just
started your career and give yourself
some advice, what would you say?
>> Sometimes I got that uh maybe I
specialized a little too early in in in
um
in programming language research.
Uh maybe
well, there there are some topics that
are I didn't learn
because I didn't feel like it. And and
that I had to relearn later or I still
have to learn now that I'm almost 60 and
maybe not not as um
uh
not as quick uh
as I was back in the day. So, yeah,
maybe I I did specialize a little too
early. And so, I would encourage
everyone to get a everyone who's serious
about working in computing uh to get a
fairly diverse computer science
background. Even even for topics that
look super theoretical and are not very
uh relevant to
uh to everyday uh
jobs.
Uh well, we mentioned the
computability for instance things like
the halting problem and so on. You're
not going to run into that very often,
but it still
gives
interesting perspectives, I think.
And then it also helps understanding new
problems.
Like
with quantum computing.
What can you do with a quantum computer
that you cannot do with a normal
computer?
And and and it's it's time to to revisit
all of the classic complexity theory I
learned earlier and when when I was
young. And and so yeah, I think I think
it's good to have those this kind of
background even if
it's not obvious you will be using it
everyday.
And and sometimes I wish I had taken
time to accumulate a little more of this
background
before specializing in in programming
languages.
>> Awesome. Well, thank you so much for
your time Professor Liwei. I appreciate
it.
>> Thank you Aaron. That was nice.
>> Hey, thank you for watching this
podcast. If you liked it and you want to
see the show grow, please support with a
comment or a like.
Also, if you have any recommendations
for people you want me to bring on,
please drop a comment. Guests like
Barbara Liskov, Mike Stonebraker, Mark
Brooker, these were all people that I
brought on because someone left a
comment. On another note, aside from the
podcast, I'm working on building the
ergonomic keyboard that I wish existed.
Here's a glance at the prototype. It's a
split keyboard, so there's two sides.
Um this is in the case. But yeah, we
launched on Kickstarter and we hit our
goal within 8 hours of launching. I
really appreciate it if you were one of
the people who grabbed one of the early
units. Um we're now working on the long
journey of building the tooling now. And
so if you still want to pick one up,
I've left the late pledges open on
Kickstarter, so you can grab one there.
I'll put a link in the description.
Thank you again for watching the podcast
and I'll see you in the next episode.